We are lives here twenty fifty build and I'm here
with the microsoft edge t so...
Spark what less introduce ourselves I got ahead of
ourselves so tell us where you are and what you do my name's understand I work on the
...microsoft edge team okay I...you so is it the same spartan
it is I don't know what the important thing is...we forgotten always got jan
...all microsoft bids that's right here and part is the like the sued I put on at night when I try to do
my...play by myself well there's that awkward for-you on
...and you who are you which you my name's charles morris I'm also pm lead on the microsoft edge
team...and I either I don't know what it could've been called before but
...so the first question that I
want first of all we are taking questions lives so if you have any questions
directive and we'll answer any questions that we can within reason obviously don't...
A huge amount of time but let's start with this.
...you start fromthe user to share so,
...approximates was I work from the app and he works in the platforms side ok so,
you are the app platform...what's the difference well my
...to build the app user experience the features,
you know, the on top of it and we work on basically the engine that
powers the browser so what...takes the html
...javascript actually renders the web page so I think we both had
...reasons to build a new thing so...yeah, so, from our perspective,
you know, ...explore for about twenty years now it would be having is
twenty-year birthday this year but it...still will...
...it's...part of the product intellectually moi.
Ugly every...is just to be clear of this...folks wonder like...is still part of windows ten
...available for compatibility and for enterprises to use but,
microsoft edge is sort of the...out of this, you know, really looking at windows ten in the opportunity
windows ten presenter respect to all the different device hypes that supports different kinds of
input types are changes in the environment over the last twenty years in terms
...security and privacy and serves...
expectation for what a browser does and how it works and,
really kind of saying do we have the right browser for the next twenty years
...can really re approach...like...rebuild a
...so that...we have some it works across pc's and phones and,
you know,...decide the whole...demo yesterday we really want,
... read think how we built...browser...the features that we have as well are really trying to you know,
comment what we've learned over the last, you know, ten fifteen years about how people
use...browser what they expects dot so you said there's a y for you yeah,
so, are audiences really web developers right and what we heard from them was really, you
know,...story where the web has been around for twenty years and it's really changed a lot
...ies been around for most the time and what happened over the
years especially the early years was that there's a lot of ie proprietary technology in there because it was filling
in gaps as the rest of the standards-based web was maturing so you
...saw things like active-x controls vp
...somebody's technology sit...actually...other browsers?
And, at the same time we had customers that needed those to continue working so we had kind of
...tension of trying to pull forward with more modern web technologies but we also had to
keep the old stuff working that only...I so
those are big reason for kind of making a break from the past and really starting out with
clean with the fresh engine that we kind of just move forward with got it
...quick question obviously if you have questions please
have them come in this make sure that they if you guys make sure that it's coming out of the
...I'm not seeing them but here's, here's the other question...what about this when I first
throughout this project is this a complete rewrite from the ground-up.
So, I think it even in this case we're also going to have to slightly different answers from
an engine perspective it is not a ground-up rewrite so,
about a year-ago we did a forks on a similar way that
other new basically almost all web rendering
...engines have started as a fork of each other right so,
the new...engine which we call microsoft edge html started out as
a fork of the ie engines so this was about a year-ago but since then it has
diverge very rapidly like there's thousands and thousands of changes to the point where,
you know, it's a separate dl and we feel comfortable
...new because it's really got a new focus it's very different from the
...so what kind of changes...thousand to yet what kind of changes are the with the
...process html or javascript so a lot of it was removing the
ie specific stuff that I talked about earlier a lot of it was making changes so that we
behaved more like other browsers again when we when we just had the one engine a lot of times
...hard to make those changes because
ie had behave like after twenty years so people expected that to
happen so now that we were freed from that we could actually start to make the new
...just work like, you know, other order other
...modern browsers so does that mean that my older websites that
I've just been out because the internet's you...tons of web is that stuff not
going to work as well as...new browser or is there compatibility issues it really
...a lot of most of the old websites work fine okay if...built on
standards technology...they're built on like html for like html tables still work
rate right if they if they are dependent on
ies specific technology so active-x is really
the big one then you're going to have to look at ie as the fallback
...okay so the question again was from his perspective
did we start from scratch and I want to see if it from your perspective...so we didn't,
you know, start with an empty, you know, cplus-plus file which is sort of I guess maybe every developers
...we kept some of the core process model the same but much like the platform
...removed a bunch of the stuff that was really this is lazy technology that we've
been had around for twenty years and then we did rewrite the entire ui so
...previous you...was a mix of...dewey and...thirty-two some different technologies and now it's
all them all ...ui and the entire sort of core was poured over...we're now a
universal windows...windows platform app which is part of what we want to achieve is that
needs...run all the platforms a support universal windows that's where the person is platforms
...upc in the phone and hollow...weird there
...a demo that as well right and...you know,
all the hold all the devices that sort of run years so in essence?
It's kind of like well we want this browser to work
...and we're promoting as a company that if you have a universal
windows app it works anywhere so why not make our browser do that
...show everyone take the lead that you can do it will work and I like all right
well we have some questions coming in from job you guys have any plans to go
...platform or will you guys
...considerate guys and gals right now we have no plans seo cross-platform are...
totally focused on making the best browser for windows ten right now that said,
you know, were as we said numerous times...always listening feedback so
...definitely continue listening got it so do you have you have
...maybe and...the cool features that we can look forward...maybe is that art
...already in the current...ethical pbs the one that came out today we've had there's
...some browser called project...a lot like...mario?
But, you try...project...the current in the current builds and,
it has many of the features we showed up a couple new ones and then
some stuff that we're working on the future in the keynote yesterday I can show you some of them today let's look
at what what's the what's the differentiation here to make it so that we need a new
...I want to see that sounds good so ...important things we did was, you know, we have this new
streamline user experience where we...have taken away a lot of the
...design point of view we've kind of...up removes number the lines and, you know,
this is sort of our new tab page that we showed our yesterday really
focus on helping people get to the sites they're interested...searches and then content this
...personalized them as well right once you...get into it we have a couple areas where we've been
...one of them is we've integrated...into the browser goal and we've
got a couple interesting ways they really looked at it as...how if you have this personal...
out your personal system help you with browser well she would sort of be there where you're sort of like, you know,
go your browser your personal system please go this website for me
...she would do is sort of...side and if you notice you doing something you can help with that she might
sort of interject...answer help with that so one of the examples, you know,
if you start typing whether like you're going to this san-francisco whether you might be like well,
you don't have to presenter and go do search...tell you what the weather is right that and, for the folks
...san-francisco this is in fact what it's like outside's...but,
there's, you know, several other things you can do a...notices that, you know, you're, you're about the search for this thing, you know,
when is, you know, thanks-giving, you know,
twenty fifteen sort of pop-up...answer that right there I'll
...it's in november I can center and do a search as well because
...little tidbits of information you don't need the whole page ds
righty information is really good with celebrities as well so I think samoa?
...as one does...you need to know...pitt is, you know,
I did that search this morning...and you don't even have to
...has to do...that are the...on the same
...I'm saving life-time here with this kind of stuff resides list is fantastic yet so, you know,
she actually is able to at answer questions like that there's a few other things we've done fewer to go to you know,
a certain different.
You type...mode.
Typing is hard it is alive on tv of your website cx what happens operating
porn there's going to popped out and...weston website odds are good I...to help you with that so you can sort
of tap on that as like give you a little packages information...elected this is,
you know, with phone-number is this is...the menus like italian is...open right now it is actually open
right now if you were close to it where this is a restaurant seattle would tell you how far away...is from where
...located back so it's sort of contextual information it's not like may
go to website this it's no like now that I'm at website this
yet what might you be interested about the size and the other example I can pick
another some random piece attacks they...on a good tell me, you know, south...union
is a neighborhood in washington give-me kind of an idea where it is as you supports a whole bunch of different...
the like different recipes like with...food use a liked to play with the nutritional value of that...you know,
and, arbitration liberty like brad pitt...you really,
really key information about backyard already the pictures which actually that turns out the most
click things for celebrities...so that's where...we've actually work...runs a couple of things
...this work with reading ok so if you we have a new reading list the sort of
...favorites but also...this is you know, stuff of added to my reading...and if I click on
...pop in over that site and then we have a rereading view that you click in which gives
...distraction free...view of the content depends, you know,
flip through the all of the their ads on the page...sort of get...to the background...focus on the
contents ...those that...the interject he's using his touch-screen as
this is happening right now you can't see...libraries all the good bad everybody has to
...asked and, then the other thing that we added is annotations also
these we call them web nodes so if...on that little but you move in this notation note-taking mode.
We're still working on is, you know, that's okay but, I've always told people when
...previewing new stuff it's like we're let-you in the house and then you look under our
...it might be clean all the way but we're still cleaning some stuff up
...so don't mind the cob webs...february dissipated but
...database effects so,...moved accidentally shun mode and now I with my finger if I wanted to I
...say this looks good I should go...
This and then I can shared or savior send it to somebody and say, you know,...
my boss...to go to that build thing that sounds good
...I saw this feature where are these annotations being...locally on your machine.
...and you can save...send that package over to,
you know, whatever you want to within...in...annotations so the opening...like a link that
...just opening the page annotations we will do that eventually...for this leases
...package over in...an attachment and email got ...survey, you know,
it's like it's reading this reading stuff the annotation stuff and,
then this...tonic feature music that paul we do reading writing and arithmetic as you can actually
also you can also do math in there and she'll play with the answers
...sometimes but...well, this the afternoon there have...more difficulty with
one-click the worker...a hard one is...is a trick in there but
anyway that would samoa art so we have some more questions coming in when will we get the option to
say webpage as web archive dot slash dot
html good question I'm not sure it's good,
you know, whether that would suggest as a lot of these kinds of things is we have a ton of feedback sports
...little smiley face...corner, you know,
we have a lot of people going through this feedback what one of the things that we're spending a lot of time on this
...like the rest of windows ten is were released in early...feedback right, you know,
we made out of thought the web archives really important thing but if, you know, that's the thing...super...for
bunch of people that's good that feedback in and then we'll prioritized on our backlog and make sure that we work on
...as a developer as developers we always get the well what about this what about that right, yeah,
we love everything but you gotta get some things done verse and for a feature requests like this
a great resources the user voice site so if you go to windows dot user voice dot
com there's a microsoft edge category which I'm sure has been renamed
...absolutely why should be reading I mean...it's always been it and,
that's a great place to add that type of features and other people can
...uk plus one plus...three provides a john
asked real extension support be available on the phone hapless only take
johnson's question as well which is...senses
...be available so what...the by...support absolutely so one of the things that we did
...showed up yesterday and the demo was we're starting to work on
...for extensions in this means the ability to add
additional functionality the browser forgot of...lot of people we use reddit, for example,
really love the...enhancement sweet for a we worked with...microsoft translate team...translation
extension that you automatically translate the content your page or we worked pinchers team and they have an
extension that basically...you in the images on your pays are actually, you know,
behind sri every...yeah, so, this is the...in this, you know,
directly to my you know,
my board on pinterest so these extensions are all you know,
built-in html javascript we started working on this they won't be available when we are tm
...summer right but we're start working on it will have sort of
insider preview available shortly after or tm we'll start working with so, you know,
that's our we don't have an exact date for...will actually go to production but we start working on it
meets if you will view of it yesterday so expenses...and we're definitely putting
that in the...in the roadmap we really wanted because it's actually...things that come up many times I
got I want extensions I want my a res someone mad...I want, you know,
these kinds of probably at the top of our feedback...at the get actually is the number one,
...user voice other than keep that old name which is the other one layout of
...likely the...people to know what the union was...the
So, john...much of it and there was a question about mobile
...we actually do want to bring to mobiles...on the roadmap it's probably will do the desktop person
unlocking...but so...you because of what universal windows apps
should yet so the cortex will work...the mobile devices have slightly different needs
gaidar the low battery there's other...dictation like, you know,
this thing can handle having...extension source the in the background doing some
...the smaller devices cat so we have to do more work around making sure that
they extensions can be more they can be shut down cleanly automatically if
...use this is a little bit more...also put in buttons
...which is right a little harder when you've got a...screen so, you're what you're saying is
...we can make it go over but we need to start making a little
...better on the advice device and that's actually true all the universal windows platform has been
our philosophy the...the same but you really want tailor to the device type
guy and make sure that, you know, it really fits into that device not one
experience everywhere it's one core everywhere and then, you know,
tailor the user experience for the different device...so john ask how much of the
...code base is shared with I so from
the platforms perspective there's no code sharing so it was a clean split the old
ie code is basically freeze dried I'll get
security fixes and that's actually good thing for customers you need that backwards compatibility
...one of the feed the feedback...edit like because we kept on changing it would break
...stuff that was written in nineteen ninety nine so,
edges completely clean split and I think the...the same is true from the...abs the same thing we don't
...the highly is there's no sharing...possess a universal
...an obviously...exports not so-if another question from...does...support
third really rendering with web...that's an easy one yes absolutely.
What we should say more...super-duper...the awesome...go-go
to flied arcade dot com which we just launched today which shows it off it's got yeah,...
here actually all let's...work that we have the technology here we go?
There ago the says
...rendering...or that looks really smote...play...go.
All right here again you're, you're on you better fly this really,
really...what you possibly go
...nothing I mean as long as we did our sacrifices the demo
...al-zoubi...all do not I
totally did okay so we're okay so this is actually a website,
...and, with web...and...technologies ads got web audio
so what we can here because we didn't we didn't hookup audio but so the throttle as I
...up and down is actually a single audio file this being
...real-time processed by javascript you kind of
shift the pitch and then it's also got game pad api support so we don't have an xbox
controller hooked up but kevin showed this morning actually controlling this game through
three-d xbox so I'm going to I'm going to go back here before I crash attending
...up...not a live...and yanking
...arcade dot com yep that's cool all right so...questions
yet what about inspect element at twelve tools right now getting...as a new window with
...you tools ok there's a couple of questions there so first of all...twelve.
Are the tools for both id as well as microsoft edge so,
they're coming forward going as we move forward the new features for adapt tools are only going
to show up in microsoft edge in terms of inspect element so they are
...inspect element I don't know if it's in the context menu yes it's in the...the most recent
build...flights roddy inspect element is coming...outdoors and I
think the other piece that was maybe like the new window piece was that we don't have docking where the
...twelve's tools are docked into the browser that they do open
...new window right now that's on our road math but,...don't have a...for
that rate dot but I mean it's beautiful I mean I'm looking at that it's it looks good,
yeah, I like it very...than a ton of work on these tools are very our like...a big
...my feeling now is applications should focus on
the content and not the...so I love the way that you
...of...of the browsers disappeared but the experiences more it feels like
you're, you're more into what the website is opposed to the to be a better using you
...jacob says microsoft...support the latest and web standards and how often do you
...updated with those standards?
That's a great question so I mean as with all things side us, you know,
which specific standards you're interested in but thank you very much wrote my
...my lovely system here has brought up status dot modern dot
...which is going to get a re brand very quickly but,
it's basically...public roadmap so this is just a ton of web standards
here all the latest stuff that is either implemented in
developments under consideration...in preview so,
we community actually filter here and show, for example?
In development or in...so this is basically a list of
...fifty-five features now that are basically they're not and I eleven but
they're either in project spartan preview or in development which
...are coming guys so this is this it and these are all very recent standards
that that's not like old stuff...new slots
...like a sm js yes like the ridiculous way of playing like unreal
games exactly in your browser so, yes, I guess the answer is status dot modern docked
...updated very regularly to answer...like multiple times
a month basically as soon as we start writing code we got flippant and development so everyone knows
got it it's actually part of a new our new approaches part of building...approach to work
with development community...just been...open as possible, you know,
we did stuff like this we do monthly tweet...we used to use the ask ie hash
...going to be a new ask microsoft edge so look for a session
there if you are follow
ad microsoft edge dev on twitter then you'll see all those announcements about the
art jim mass is the ui entirely made with the universal api I guess
...means universal up...program how...the thing was...hard to make a
...of universal windows platform well frankly what we did was you know,
part of as you said earlier on like us moving this browser over to the universal windows
platform that's right is about actually helping the platform get better so that was a requirement that we had of
...of the platform is that we would be able to put our tabs up on the title bar
...what they did was they said great that's a feature that you guys want windows...apps
...same thing as a basically gave us an api as with...api there's maybe...as
a we like to write we'd like to draw the title ourselves and that's what we had a now abs three able to
do that as well I...what people are noticing is that this is a beautiful
universal windows app can I borrow some of the conventions that...gradients actually
...platform network...call...the app developers full benefit from you got
so the question here is their way for a web page to identify work was coming from so,
the...yes and surprisingly
the way is to detect the edge token...user agent string so,
with that settles I will say that we are definitely encouraging web
developers to not detect edge explicitly
this especially for the core web page content is one of our main
...for forking at the engine as I said earlier was to make sure that developers don't have to write
ie specific coder edge specific code now so,
there are certain good reasons like if you're advertising and app banner something that you want to make sure people get to the right
app stored that's a good reason to detect the browser but if you're seeing a bug
...behaving differently across browsers you may need to put that in that work around
...temporarily but we want
...that feedbacks that we can go figure out okay do we need to make a change does google or missile
...to make changes we work with them to try to make web platform consistent
...really the promise of the web its can write cross-platform so it's like
yes you can but if you're doing it maybe we need to look at
...send...feedback especially if there's a bug that you think he found... it's like that
...I'll go ahead...the how will update were...it...
stand-alone that's a good question what I make sure we talked about that because one of our goals with both with windows
...general is that it is updated regularly and...were,
you know, using windows tend...are always...the latest version of the platform
...applies equally to microsoft edge...you want to keep moving forward I think the common
...industries keep evergreen...you're always using that latest version has been one of
...issues that we've been dealing with over the years with ie is the
...fragmented...ten so we...make sure that, you know, people are using microsoft as
there always use that they always have that latest version...as...we roll it out
...will be updated by...sort of windows updates and,
by the store our time so you...come...the users so you're just going
to get this update automatic yep absolutely got it well that's good for web developers
...that means you can always ehow on that same versions...being there
...good will there be a web store for extensions where
users can submit the...firefox I think that goes into the
...when we have extensibility we I mean it...apps are
...the windows store will have will be the place...users go to get...and that's...
really important for us because it helps make sure...habit trust in the extensions
of...extensions...do what they say...to do got another question is
...to xbox any integration with comptroller to allow web
geo that's an interesting because it's a universal windows app it should work?
the xbox part is, you know, edge will eventually come to xbox one...those who have
...our road map not we don't have a announcers when that's...sort of like the same story
...the phone...certain optimizations we gotta do and we...we're focusing on...outburst, yeah,
absolutely and the second piece is absolutely so we showed game pad working with flied
arcade so that one of the reasons we did that was anticipating it going to
the xbox so it's great for games all right so if the current you why the final one
if so are there any plans of the roadmap to allow for more complex specific use
case customizations it's pretty close we think is the final ui for
tm we're always open to feedback, you know, you the user voice
site hit the smiley face tell us what you like what kinds of customizations that you'd like
for us to do I mean we are billion browser that's what's good about this sort of environment
we're building we want people to lovett and bribery thinks that it should be
...this way then we'll certainly consider putting that functionality just finish up because
I'm running out of time how hard will it be to center...that...this...a
...that's a web developer everyone moi.
Because...there's like sites devoted to this yet it's a
joke obviously you're going to do whatever the standards are.
All right...thanks for...blink tag thank you got you guys...lillian,
you know, of course...backward will thanks so much for watching
...so much for spending some time with...setting the look at this and if there's any questions again you have the user
...want to go-there smoothly...are watching and I think we're going to wrap it up
...shows today we'll see you tomorrow we're here to build twenty fifteen take care.